It is
a privilege to be a detective.
Mark Birch: You deal
with lots and lots of
horrible things,
that comes with the territory.
The majority of us
don't have to see these things,
don't have to
deal with these things.
The launch of the fifth
murder enquiry in such
a short space of time...
Martin Brunning: Justice
for the victims is absolutely
the most important thing.
- You've been arrested
on suspicion of attempted
murder and murder.
- Could be worse.
Officer PTC: We can
only imagine the grief of
the families who lost
their loved ones in such brutal
circumstances.
- ... with your DNA.
How can that be?
- No comment.
Journalist PTC: The judge
said the murder showed
a degree of
premeditation and planning.
He'd been stabbed and beaten.
Howard Groves: It was very
much a manhunt at that stage
of the investigation.
He knew that the walls
were closing in on him.
Stewart Gull: I always remember
a more experienced officer
telling me, you know, you,
you never forget these jobs,
and he was right.
VO: These are the detectives
who solved some of Britain's
most notorious homicides.
Now they re-live those cases.
Martin Brunning: Every fear
that I had was being realised in
front of my eyes.
VO: Through every twist and Turn of the investigation ...
Mark Birch: The only way you
forget about it is ...
is when you're asleep.
VO: Their personal accounts
reveal what it really takes
to capture a killer
and bring them to justice.
Howard Groves:
As a detective, you know,
there, there can't be any
greater honour than for you
to investigate the death- or
murder- of another human being.
Martin PTC: This investigation has so many shocking elements
to it,
one after the other.
And at no stage when this
investigation started did it
ever occur to me that
the person responsible for
so much damage was a woman.
Martin PTC: What makes a
murder case different
from other cases?
The impact of your actions
will always be remembered
by the people
affected by that murder.
And absolutely crucial
that it's the right memory.
Until the person that we are
after is safely locked away
from society, I don't rest.
And my team recognise the
importance of what we're doing
on behalf of the victim.
The person with no
Voice, we're doing it for them.
Martin PTC: This
case started in Easter in,
er, twenty-thirteen,
the Bank Holiday weekend.
I was working as the Major Crime
Senior Investigator covering
Bedfordshire, Cambridgeshire
and Hertfordshire.
Martin PTC: Around
nine-sixteen a 999 call was
received by the
fire service in Cambridgeshire.
A couple of guys had come
across a car fire in
the village of Yaxley.
VO: Unknown to police,
that car fire at Yaxley
is connected to something
far more disturbing waiting
on the other
side of Peterborough.
Martin PTC: I was
on the A1 between Huntingdon
and Peterborough and
the phone rang in the car
and it was one of the,
the DI's from Peterborough said
'Look, a body's turned up,
by a dog-walker, in a ditch'.
VO: It was a villager
walking his dog who found
the body off a single
track road near Peterborough.
Journalist PTC: The body was
found here after half past
ten on Saturday morning,
close to Newborough and the A16.
Martin PTC: I was told that
visually the person looked like
the photo that we had as part
of a missing person enquiry.
It felt like there was
going to be really bad
news on the end of this.
Martin PTC:
I went straight to the scene.
So I'm driving down this farm
track and I see the police
car ahead and I stop
my car close by and I decided
to walk through a field
and it was- I had a suit on-
it was muddy,
it was just difficult to get to,
and it was freezing cold.
It was a really
cold Easter weekend.
And eventually I, I found
a route in towards the body
and straight away was struck
by the position of, of the body.
The first thing I thought
was that somebody was
humiliating this person.
In all of my experience,
this stood out as 'fixed'.
It had been framed, whoever did
this wanted people to see it.
Martin PTC: The position
of this man was that he was
in a ditch and his buttocks
were pointing very clearly
up towards the sky.
And, and it was, it felt
and looked very much like he,
he'd been put
in that position to degrade him.
He was wearing a black sequinned
dress which was obviously a,
a woman's garment, um, but it'd
been pulled right up above
his waist and it,
it was just the strangest thing.
Martin PTC: So I could see
blood on his arms and at that
stage I, I don't know
how this man has died so the,
the critical questions for me
are: What are we dealing with?
Is it a murder?
Is this misadventure?
And it was really, really
obvious when we turned him
over onto his
back that he'd been murdered.
He'd been stabbed.
Centrally located stab wounds.
He'd got injuries on his
forearm and between his fingers.
Defence wounds
where a hand had really,
had obviously
been put up to stop the force,
which said to me that this
is a really violent way to die.
Martin PTC: I'm starting to
look around and I'm standing
in a field
for as far as the eye can see,
it felt like
it was the middle of nowhere.
There's no cameras,
there's no witnesses,
this is a really
difficult terrain to start
a murder investigation.
And I'm starting
to think Why a dress?
How did he die?
What's it going
to take to unravel this job?
VO: Police quickly confirm
the identity of the victim in
the ditch as 48-year-old
missing local man Kevin Lee.
VO: What police knew
of Kevin's life threw little
light on his violent death.
Martin PTC: Kevin was to all
intents and purposes a family
man, he had a business in
Peterborough renting properties,
and had a lovely family.
Had a lovely family.
Kevin was, um,
a genuinely empathetic man.
He would give accommodation
to people who had certain
vulnerabilities, and that
was certainly a trait in
a number of his tenants.
He was showing a
huge amount of, um,
support for people that
just needed a leg-up in life.
There was no logical explanation
at that point that I was stood
looking into that ditch
to explain or account
why Kevin was, was there
and in those circumstances.
VO: Kevin's disappearance
had been reported by his wife
barely twelve hours earlier.
Martin PTC: Kevin went
missing around six o'clock in
the evening on Good Friday.
Er, should have been at home, didn't come back.
Kevin's wife was
clearly concerned,
it's completely
out of character for him.
And she kind of started
her own police investigation,
for want of a better term.
She identified from his online
mobile phone account people
that he'd been in contact with, or numbers that had
contacted his phone,
and she just randomly started
calling people as any...
Fearful wife perhaps would do.
She never particularly knew who
she was speaking to but would,
would ask the
questions, 'Have you seen Kevin,
he's not come home?'
And around
quarter past nine she makes, er,
one of a number of telephone
calls and the call connected
for two seconds
before the call was dropped.
That phone
call was absolutely crucial.
That two seconds
of telecommunications data
was enough to identify
the location of the phone,
and it was within
the precise location of
the car fire in Yaxley.
VO: That burnt-out
car belonged to Kevin Lee.
The mobile phone, almost
certainly, to his murderer.
Martin PTC: Kevin's wife,
she didn't know it but
she was talking to the
person that killed her husband.
This is a
real breakthrough moment.
If we can unpick
who owns that telephone,
we've got the key
to this investigation,
as to who killed Kevin.
VO: Using cell site analysis,
police quickly
have their answer.
Martin PTC: That phone
belonged to Joanne Dennehy.
Looking at the circumstances,
there's Kevin in the ditch,
in a dress, a really violent
attack with a knife ...
I never assumed that
this was the work of a woman.
We researched Joanne Dennehy.
She was a,
a local to Peterborough.
She's a relatively
low-level criminal.
She was troubled in adulthood,
um, and was fairly anti-social.
VO: Joanne is also the
mother of two children who
live elsewhere
with their father.
Martin PTC: We make some
enquiries and after speaking
to Kevin's business partner
it was very clearly obvious
that Joanne knew Kevin as
a landlord and business owner.
VO: Police now have a
prime suspect and a location
to investigate - the bedsit
that Joanne rents from Kevin.
Martin PTC: We go into
her house, we get a warrant,
we're going in, we're
going to see what we can find.
VO: The police don't
find Joanne at the property.
But they
do make a sinister discovery.
Martin PTC: In the garden
of this property is
a single mattress
which is soaked in blood.
VO: Detective
Martin Brunning: has a vicious
murder case on his hands
and a prime suspect at large.
The hunt is on to find her.
Martin PTC: I was content at
that point that Joanne
Dennehy was a suspect
in the murder of Kevin Lee,
and all the energy over that
weekend was to get our hands
on her as quickly as possible.
Martin PTC: There's a, a
heavily bloodstained mattress
in a house
in Byfield where Joanne lived,
and I'm thinking 'Is
this where Kevin was killed?'
But I'm also being told that
one of the tenants is missing.
Martin PTC: A guy called
John Chapman who was vulnerable,
should have
been there, wasn't.
This man who I'm told leads
this simple lifestyle
of drinking and sleeping
and never venturing too far
from the house is not there.
Where is he?
So is it a missing guy
or is it something terrible's
happened to him?
And I'm thinking if it's
something terrible's happened
to him, and
we've actually got two murders,
then how much of a risk is
she to the public that
she's not going to stop?
VO: Acutely
aware of the public risk,
detective Brunning
widens the net.
Martin PTC: I put her picture
in the media over that weekend.
We know she's distinctive, she's
got this tattoo on her face,
and I'm thinking we're going to
get a line of enquiry from this.
We're going to
get a breakthrough,
somebody's going to say
'I've just seen Joanne Dennehy,
I've seen why you want her,'
and I'm thinking we're going
to get control around
this really, really quickly.
VO: It soon becomes apparent
that wherever Joanne is,
she's not alone.
Martin PTC: We identify
that there's a very strong
correlation between her mobile
phone activity and that of an
associate called Gary Stretch.
Martin PTC: Over that
weekend it is clear that Joanne
was evading the police.
We could see from her,
the movement of her telephone
that she was turning
it on, she was turning it off.
She, she clearly needed to use
it from time to time and it was
obvious from Gary's phone that
he was turning it on and off.
And when we overlaid the imagery
of where that was happening it
was as clear as day that those
two were in company together,
on the run, knew
they were wanted by the police,
and were doing all they
could to avoid being captured.
VO: Joanne and Gary had done
odd jobs together for Kevin Lee,
including collecting rent and
dealing with difficult tenants.
Martin PTC: Gary is a
career criminal in Peterborough.
He's been dubbed, er, 'Britain's
Tallest Burglar'- a giant of a
man at seven-foot-three.
If these two are
together, even more distinctive,
even more reason
to put them into the media.
The public are go
... going to see these two,
er, together and
think 'Actually, I've seen that,
I've seen that on the news'.
So I was really excited about
that and hoped that that
would give us the opportunity
to, to get them arrested really,
really quickly.
VO: Now the police have
released pictures of two people
they want to question in
connection with the stabbing-
Gary Stretch
who is 47 and seven-foot-three,
and Joanne Dennehy who is 30
with a distinctive green tattoo.
Police urge anyone with
any information to come forward.
Martin PTC:
And we get nothing.
For the whole weekend-
it's Easter,
people are with their families,
they're not looking at the news,
they're not interested.
This woman is roaming
around the east of England,
I don't know where she is,
I don't know what she's doing,
but what I do know is that
the public are at risk if
she's not in custody.
Martin PTC: I was in the
canteen at Police Headquarters,
I'd just bought a cup of coffee
and I was talking to a colleague
about 'stuff', the job that we
were investigating and I'd got
the information to say 'Oh,
we've just taken a phone call
from a, a Norfolk bobby who's
got a registration number of the
car, and thinks it's Dennehy'.
And I said
'Oh, thanks very much'.
And I carried on the
conversation and it wasn't until
about a minute in I thought
... 'We've got the registration
number of the car'.
It was like this
moment of realisation.
I was so engrossed in the
conversation that I kinda turned
on my heels and flew across to
the Major Incident Room
and said 'Right, let's get this
registration number into ANPR,
Automatic Number
Plate Recognition,
I want to know
where it is, Iet's track it'.
VO: A minor theft eighty
miles away had given a clue
to Joanne's
possible whereabouts.
Martin PTC: A detective in
Norfolk - he was investigating
a shoplifting where a car had
driven onto the forecourt
of a petrol
station just outside of Cromer,
and had recognised the
similarity of a female who'd
got out of the passenger seat
and went into the, the store,
stole a whole load of
groceries and food and then
got back in the car.
Martin PTC: And that was
the absolute breakthrough
in order to, to, to
start to track Joanne and Gary.
We were able to start
honing down really where
that vehicle was.
We recognised that
it was a green Vauxhall Astra,
that it had been activating ANPR
all around the east of England,
that in fact at one
stage we were getting live
time notifications that
the car was travelling on
the M5 south-west towards
the West Mercia police area.
VO: A local murder hunt
has now become a three-county
investigation.
Martin PTC: We were straight on
the phone to West Mercia
saying 'Look, this
car has got these people in it,
they've certainly killed
one person in Cambridgeshire,
you need to get your hands
on them and please ring me
when you've done it'.
And it was as,
as fast-moving as that.
It was exhilarating,
it was pressured,
it was we're nearing the end,
we're going to get our hands
on these people and, and then
we can put our foot on
the ball and take
stock of exactly what's gone on.
VO: As sightings come in,
Martin's team is able to piece
together an audacious picture
of Joanne and Gary's movements
over the Bank Holiday weekend.
The evidence shows Dennehy
and Stretch walking into
the services
on the M5, hand in hand,
without a care in the world.
Martin PTC: They were
breaking into people's houses,
stealing food, stealing
cameras to turn into cash
whilst on the run.
Martin PTC: They were taking
pictures of themselves in
towns throughout
the east of England.
It was an elaborate
cops-and-robbers event that
they added and weaved
into an element of fun,
that it was thrilling,
it was exciting,
they were untouchable,
and this romantic relationship
that was blossoming whilst on
the run from the police has
so many parallels to Bonnie
and Clyde that
it, it's almost beyond belief.
VO: Martin and his team wait
nervously for news from West
Mercia Police.
Martin PTC: I'm literally
pacing up and down the, the,
the Major Incident Room waiting
for the phone call to say we've
got her, we've got him.
That sense of pheww, pressure's
off, and it doesn't come.
And I'm getting
increasingly anxious.
What I anticipated
would happen is,
is that the cops in West Mercia
would come across the vehicle,
they would stop
it, they would lock them up,
and we would get a phone call.
How wrong was I.
Martin PTC: Eventually that
phone call comes but it comes
with the caveat that there's
been a whole load of carnage
in Hereford.
VO: Involved in that carnage,
two people matching Joanne
and Gary's descriptions.
Martin PTC: The information
that we were getting was that
Gary and, and Joanne were
together in Hereford in
the car and Joanne
had attacked two strangers.
Two men horrendously
with a knife within
a ten-minute timeframe.
Which realised every fear
that I had about just what
she was capable of doing.
VO: Those two men
were 64-year-old Robin Bereza,
attacked while walking his dog,
as was 56-year-old John Rogers.
John PTC:
She was stabbing in, my chest.
She said,
um, 'Look, you're bleeding,
I'd better do some more'.
And I think I said
'Just leave me alone please.
Please leave me alone.' And then
when it did finally stop, um,
I just thought well this
is it, I'm, I'm going to die.
VO: John Rogers received
more than thirty stab wounds.
Both he and Robin Bereza barely
survived the Unprovoked attacks.
Martin PTC: We've
got one murdered, one missing,
two fighting for their lives, so
it was a very kind of sobering
phone call
for a whole host of reasons.
Martin PTC:
Joanne was on a killing spree.
She had done
two, she wanted to do some more,
she had
those conversations with Gary,
it was very clear that until
the cops intervened
and stopped her
she was going to carry on.
VO: Joanne Dennehy
is wanted for murder in
Peterborough and has been
seen stabbing two more
victims in Hereford.
At ten past four on
Tuesday afternoon West Mercia
Police finally bring
her violent rampage to an end.
Martin PTC: We are
told that eventually, er,
Joanne and Gary have been
arrested, they're in custody,
the public were safe.
But it
came at a terrible cost in, er,
Robin Bereza and John
Rogers suffering such
terrible injuries.
VO: When Joanne is arrested
she shows little of
the blood lust that's
fuelled her brutal attacks.
Martin PTC: Joanne was caught
in the vehicle which had
parked up after
the second stabbing.
She was a passenger in the front
seat, er, she was very calm.
She engaged with the officers
and even produced the knife
that she had just used
on the two men in Hereford
and handed it
over to the officers.
VO: Joanne is brought
to Hereford Police Station
for booking.
- Afternoon.
- And you are?
- Joanne Christina Dennehy.
- So you've been arrested
on suspicion of attempted
murder and murder, ok?
Martin PTC: Joanne presented at
the custody desk as if she
was in a really euphoric
state and the video that I saw
subsequently showed her in
a really relaxed frame of mind.
- Would you be cheery
if you were up for attempted
murder and murder?
- I wouldn't but ...
- No, but I'm still smiling.
- I don't know
anything about it.
I was just out
enjoying the sunshine.
- You'll be reading about
it in the newspapers shortly.
- Say again.
- You'll be reading about
it in the newspapers shortly.
- Well I'll look forward to it.
- You're a decent copper.
I'm a crap killer, ain't I?
- Well you've been caught so ...
Martin PTC: She was joking
with the officers that were,
er, escorting her.
Her humour was
really inappropriate.
- It could be worse.
I could
be big, fat, black and ugly.
- You could be what?
- Big, fat, black and ugly.
- Yeah you could be.
- So it could be worse.
- I'm not sure
how that would be worse though.
- Yeah it would.
- Would it?
- Yeah.
- You've got very
distinctive eyebrows.
- I know, so you keep saying.
- Now everyone's
looking at your eyebrows.
- We've got some suitable
clothing for you to wear Joanne.
- A tracksuit and plimsolls?
- Could well be.
- And a tracksuit top.
- Ey it's better
than nothing innit?
- Fucking glamorous that is.
Martin PTC:
Just strange, strange behaviour.
It was as if she'd
partitioned it off and this
was all one big joke.
And that she
was at the centre of this joke.
- Right, so what am I up for?
Attempted murder and murder?
- You've been arrested
on suspicion of attempted
murder and murder.
- Could be worse.
- Thanks.
- You're welcome.
- That's lovely.
- Not bad for a murderer.
- It's a
good one actually, yeah.
Martin
PTC: All eyes were on her,
you got a sense that she really
enjoyed it and was playing
up to it as if it was a crowd
there for her entertainment.
- No, it's nothing!
- Right, come on then Joanne.
- Can I have some food first?
- I'll take your
order when you get in the cell.
What do you want to drink?
- I feel like
the incredible hulk.
VO: Amongst the jokes, Joanne
makes a chilling revelation.
Martin PTC: She told
the custody officer at the time,
in a kind of prancing around
the, the custody room style,
that she'd killed five people.
Did she mean in her calculation
that the five people that
she'd killed included
John Rogers and Robin Bereza?
Have we got more murders?
Um, how, how does this kind
of progress, how does it unfold?
We've got the complexity
of a murder in Cambridgeshire,
we've got two people that are,
sound like they're going to die
in Hereford, and actually
it's a really pressurised time.
Really pressured.
Martin PTC: So Tuesday we
all go home knowing that
Joanne is in custody.
We all felt slightly more
at ease by the fact that we
knew she was locked away.
We planned to reconvene
on the Wednesday, take stock,
work out what was important
and really think about what
we were going to do next.
Martin PTC: On Wednesday I
came into work to start to join
the, the investigation in West
Mercia with Cambridgeshire
and as I was briefing the team
the phone on the desk next to me
rang and I picked it up and
it was the force Control Room
saying, er, we've had a report
that a body has been found
in a ditch in Thorney Dyke.
And instinctively I thought...
that's going
to be John Chapman.
We hadn't
explained his absence,
he was so close
to Dennehy in lifestyle terms,
living in the same house, this
is going to be John Chapman.
Martin PTC: Before I'd had
a chance to do anything
or make any
decision, the phone rang again.
I'll never forget this phone
call for as long as I live.
It said, 'Are you aware of
the body that has been found
in Thorney Dyke?'
And I said,
'Yes, I've just been briefed'.
And the woman
in the Control Room said to me,
'There's two bodies'.
And it stunned me.
And I held the
phone to my chest and just said,
'There's two bodies'.
And you could hear a pin drop.
And I had this - the only way
I can describe it is a rush of
adrenaline of What is going on?
What's happening?
When's this going to stop?
However bad it has been
up to this point with Kevin,
Robin Bereza, John Rogers,
however bad that has been for
those people and those families,
this has just got
a whole lot worse.
That phone call
absolutely changed the game.
And I realised that if this was
the work of Joanne Dennehy
we're dealing
with a serial killer.
Martin PTC: So I went
down to Thorney Dyke
and saw a remarkably
similar landscape to Newborough,
where Kevin's body was dumped.
A ditch alongside a field with
very little human habitation,
and quite a shocking scene
actually of two bodies side
by side, no more
than a few inches between them.
VO: For Detective Brunning
there's a sickening feeling
of déjà vu.
Martin PTC: It was
obvious that there was a huge,
huge similarity with the
circumstances of Kevin's death,
in that there were stab
wounds in the chest of both men,
localised to the
heart area, and in some numbers.
And again, indicative
of really ferocious attack.
I ... I've been in to countless
murder scenes but I wouldn't be
a human being with a beating
heart in my body if I didn't
look at that,
and look down in this case,
at those two bodies and think
... it's two more families that
I've got to
send officers to, er,
and tell them the news that
their loved ones are killed.
VO: One of the bodies in the
ditch closely resembles
Joanne's former housemate.
Martin PTC: One looked
distinctly like John Chapman.
Next to him was the body of, of
a complete stranger - stranger
to the investigation - and
I distinctly remember looking at
those two bodies and thinking Mr
Unknown - as he was at the time
- has been there
much, much longer than John has.
What does this mean for the
timeline of this investigation?
And for me it meant
that Joanne's killing spree had
started much earlier.
VO: Martin and his team now
have two injured, three dead,
and no idea
what the final tally might be.
Martin PTC: How many more
phone calls are we going to
get to say bodies
have been dumped in ditches?
How many more
people has she killed?
When the hell
is this going to stop?
Martin PTC: The prime line
of enquiry now was to confirm
the identity
of who I thought was John.
Er, we very quickly did that
... and we needed to identify
this unknown man.
Martin PTC: We got mobile
fingerprint scan technology down
to the scene and very quickly
identified that the man next
to John was
Lukasz Slaboszewski.
Thirty-one-year-old Lukasz
had settled in Peterborough
from Poland
eight years earlier.
Martin PTC: We
knew very little about Lukasz,
he lived a
fairly simple lifestyle.
It was absolutely crucial to
understand when Joanne Dennehy
started the killing spree.
Lukasz Slaboszewski
was a complete wild card
to this investigation.
What is the relevance
of Lukasz meeting his death
at the hands of Joanne
Dennehy and being in that ditch?
Perhaps that would then
lead on to why Kevin died
and why John
Chapman died.
VO: Forensic attention
turns back to the house
where Joanne
and John Chapman had bedsits.
Martin PTC: That heavily
bloodstained mattress in a house
in Byfield where Joanne lived,
we get the DNA profile
of the blood
from that mattress.
This is John Chapman's blood.
VO: The evidence Martin's
team has gathered pointing
to Joanne Dennehy as
a serial killer is stacking up.
Police have the body
and a bloody crime scene
for John Chapman.
VO: Now the focus of
the investigation turns
to Lukasz Slaboszewski.
Martin PTC: As you can imagine
and - and the investigation's
huge now - um, and a number
of people that we were
speaking to as
witnesses was in triple figures.
And one person that we
spoke to told us that
she had met Joanne at
a time before Kevin was killed,
and she had been shown a
decomposing body of a man
dumped in a wheelie
bin in the Peterborough area.
Yes, of course we would have
wanted to know about that but
the reality was,
given their age,
I don't bear
any grudge to that individual.
But Joanne chose
to traumatise her.
VO: This new information
leads police to another
of Kevin Lee's
properties at Rolleston Garth.
Martin PTC: The forensic
picture is you can see two clear
murder scenes.
There were two killings
at that property, days apart,
evidence that
Lukasz Slaboszewski was stabbed
repeatedly in
the property and bled profusely.
And there was a significant
amount of evidence to show that
Kevin Lee subsequently
died in that property,
with blood
distributed around the house.
A clean-up
operation was clearly visible.
We could show that Dennehy
and Stretch were in that
crime scene at the
time it was being cleaned up,
which linked them perfectly
to the totality of their
Involvement
in this investigation.
Gary does the disposing
of the bodies and the driving,
and the cleaning up.
Dennehy does the killing.
That's the arrangement, that was
the Bonnie and Clyde image that
the two of them wanted to
portray on their killing sprees.
Martin PTC:
This case is surreal.
If you sat in a pub with
one of your friends and tried
to recreate
a story that a woman would,
would go around the streets
of Peterborough killing men
for fun, times three,
going on the run...
savagely attacking two
men at random and then
laugh at the world
after so much damage...
all this was
being played out in real life.
VO: Detective Martin
Brunning: is dealing with
the rarest
of serial killers - a woman.
One whose killings display an
extraordinary control
over her victims.
Martin PTC: Joanne Dennehy
in her own right is quite
slight but somehow she managed
to overpower three men in such
a way as to be able to deliver
such catastrophic injuries.
Martin PTC: In all three cases
what was really interesting
about the nature of the injuries
was ... there had to be
an element of her
controlling the circumstances.
It wasn't random, it wasn't
Robin Bereza and John Rogers
in Hereford,
the frenzied set-upon mentality.
These were localised
to the centre of the chest,
around the heart.
She had the capability
and the capacity to
do that unchallenged.
And we started to establish a
greater understanding of
Joanne and her ... ability
to manipulate, to instil fear,
to use emotion
to control other people.
VO: For Joanne, emotional
seduction provided opportunity.
Martin PTC: In
Kevin's case, and Lukasz's case,
there was probably an emotional
dimension to the relationship
and she would have exploited
that to get herself physically
in a position to be able to
inflict the level and nature
of ferocity that she did.
VO: A few days after her
arrest by West Mercia police,
Joanne is released
to the Cambridgeshire force
for interrogation.
POLICE OFFICER: Did
you murder Lukasz Slaboszewski?
JOANNE DENNEHY: No comment.
POLICE OFFICER:
Did you murder John Chapman?
JOANNE DENNEHY: No comment.
POLICE OFFICER:
Did you murder Kevin Lee?
JOANNE DENNEHY: No comment.
Martin PTC: We interviewed
Joanne at length but there
were no answers.
VO: In preparation
for the pre-trial hearing,
Dennehy is subjected to
a full psychiatric examination.
VO: But Joanne refuses the
opportunity for any disorders to
be taken into consideration,
wanting full ownership of her
crimes and recognition
as a notorious serial killer.
Martin PTC: She has controlled
how she behaves at every
juncture on every level.
She behaved in a way that
she wanted the public to see.
That's the person that
Joanne is, she calls the shots.
VO: At Joanne's hearing
she has one last hand to play.
Martin PTC: I was sat
in the Old Bailey in a packed
courtroom, and crucially with
many family members there from,
from the victims of this.
All of the
evidence was going to be tested,
everything
that we'd done held to proof,
and for this to become a very
long complicated trial at some
point in the future.
VO: The time comes for
Dennehy to answer to
the three charges of murder.
Martin PTC: The clerk stood up
and read out the indictments to
formally invite Dennehy
to plead Guilty or Not Guilty.
And in, in anybody's estimation
and, and my own included,
I did not for one second
anticipate that the plea was
going to be
anything other than Not Guilty.
On the first indictment
read she pleaded Guilty,
to everybody's astonishment.
And I recall being sat directly
behind her Counsel and his
reaction was
one of absolute bewilderment.
He looked at her as
much as to say 'What you doing?
This wasn't what we agreed.
This isn't the
instruction that you gave me'.
And the second indictment was
read and she pleaded Guilty to
that, and the third
indictment was read
and she pleaded Guilty to that.
Nobody expected
what was happening.
It was an absolute farce.
But when I reflect on it now,
it was Dennehy's finest moment.
She had the whole
court room under her spell,
she had everybody
looking at her,
and she knew in process terms
this was the last chance
for her to have
control over what was happening.
VO: Joanne's pleas
have one welcome consequence.
Martin PTC: Dennehy made
it absolutely clear that she was
pleading Guilty to all of this.
And I really...
will never forget actually
a sense of relief.
Not because of the fact
that she'd admitted what she had
done, but actually the families
weren't going to have to sit
and listen to all of the gore
and the horror of her behaviour.
And I, and I
fe ... I felt so relieved that,
that they weren't going
to have to be put through that.
VO: Someone who once
knew Joanne well is her former
partner, her children's father.
I weren't too surprised if
I'm honest because of the way,
how aggressive she was.
But to murder three people?
I think I've
had a lucky escape.
I've been emotionally battered,
she just drained every bit that
I had, she was happiest when
she was doing the wrong thing.
I don't know, even today
I still, I feel cold about it.
I was with that woman, I've got
two kids with her but...
why would you
do that to your kids?
And why would you
put them through that?
VO: Three months later
Joanne Dennehy returns to
the Old Bailey to be sentenced
by Mr. Justice Spencer.
Matt Teale (newsreader):
The serial killer Joanne Dennehy
will spend the rest of her life
in prison after killing three
men and attempting
to kill two others in Hereford.
Martin PTC: Dennehy
was sentenced to a whole-life
tariff, which means
she'll never come out
and that's absolutely right.
And that's really important for
the families that she'll
never be allowed
out to hurt other people.
I remember walking out
of the Old Bailey that day
and thinking I did
what I set out to achieve.
And that is really important.
For me, the best possible
outcome for a murder case is
that justice is delivered.
We can't bring the people
back but we can help families
to move on.
Martin PTC: There's a,
a really important photograph
of Joanne as a,
as a really young girl in a blue
chequered school uniform that came into the investigation.
We were all looking at
that photograph saying
we've got kids.
I've got a daughter, and her
family would have looked at that
as her school photo at some
point in the past as a young
girl and thought
what a lovely little girl.
Full of promise,
full of hope, full of future.
But somewhere
along the line she turned bad.
And I guess we all privately
think when is that tipping
point, when that youngster in
that school uniform became the
monster that is Joanne Dennehy?
VO: There's one part
of the puzzle Martin has been
unable to solve.
Martin PTC: One
of the real frustrations, er,
and probably the biggest
unanswered question - through
all of this - is Why?
To be able
to say to all of those families,
'This is why
your loved one died'.
We've never, ever had
the privilege of Joanne Dennehy
having
the decency to tell us that.
And I suspect that
will remain the case forever.
VO: Joanne Dennehy's case
is one Detective Brunning
will never forget.
Martin PTC: Investigations
like this leave their mark,
and they leave their mark
on everybody that comes
into contact with it.
The twists, the turns,
the way it shocked,
the way it felt
out of control at times,
the level of damage that she's
done to families fundamentally
changes you as a person.
It's always your loved ones that
don't see you for days on end.
The personal cost at
the time is great but absolutely
driven to do the very
best you can for those
people that are
so deeply affected.